in the 19th century one of the most
important philosophers in Europe were
soaring Kierkegaard and though we're not
going to be looking at care guard today
I just want to mention in passing that
he was known affectionately
as the Danish gadfly that little
expression gadfly refers to somebody
that kind of stirs the pot by flittering
around from the group to group and and
engaging people in serious discussions
and thought well the first philosopher
in history that was known as a gadfly
was Socrates Socrates was called the
gadfly of Athens because of the
controversy in which he was engaged by
trying to folk people to think more
deeply than they were accustomed to
doing Socrates is famous for initiating
the phrase the unexamined life
is not worth living
and his passion was to get people to do
just that to examine their lives to
examine their thinking not to just
accept ideas uncritically because they
were in Vogue or because they were
popular but he wanted to lead them to a
kind of self-critical analysis to
challenge assumptions that were accepted
just by the transfer from one generation
to the next
and he lived at a critical period in
history not only for the history of the
Greek world but for the history of
Western Civilization
in fact some people have argued
that ancient Greek civilization was at
such a critical moment when Socrates
appeared on the scene that he not only
saved the civilization of his own Nation
but that he was the at least temporary
savior of Western civilization in his
time
now to understand that kind of an
evaluation we have to take a step back
and look at some of the background
Socrates was born
approximately in the year
468 BC now I don't mean by that that he
was approximately born he actually and
truly was born but we don't know exactly
what year it was but it was probably
468 469
b c
and that was a very important time in
Greek history because Socrates grew up
in Athens
and lived in the first instance During
the period of the highest success and
power of the Greek Nation up until that
point and particularly the greatest
success of Athens but it was also during
his life
that the wars came to pass between the
city-state of Athens and the city-state
of Sparta
you remember the adage that the Spartans
had who trained their young men to be
Warriors and when they would go off to
war with their Shields the maxim that
was given to the young Soldier was you
come back with your Shield
or on it
that is you fight to the death well what
happened during Socrates life was that
Sparta defeated
Athens
and what followed that war was a period
of unraveling of Greek culture and a
period of great skepticism and
disillusionment that gripped the
citizens of Athens now it wasn't simply
the political and Military circumstances
that brought this malays to the culture
of Athens but if you recall in our last
lecture we saw the impasse that arose
between the two great thinkers prior to
Socrates Parmenides and heraclitus and
in simple terms what many of the common
people were saying was wait a minute
what about this whole Endeavor of
searching for ultimate truth and for
Ultimate Reality it seems like a Fool's
errand to us maybe the Skeptics are
right that such truth is beyond the
scope of our ability to discover it
and they they would think like this if
the titans of intellectual
uh inquiry like Parmenides and
heraclitus can't agree on Ultimate
issues
how can you expect us to sort all of
these complex metaphysical questions out
so what happened with the decay in the
military power economic power and
political power of Athens coupled with
this sense of frustration of trying to
gain ultimate truth
the culture kind of disintegrated and
grew inward in its attention and began
to focus their thinking on this world
on
concrete practical matters we can't
figure out these ultimate questions of
truth but we're still faced with the
daily questions of how do we make a
living how do we face the the uh the
Necessities that life imposes upon us
from day to day
so we have really the the birth of
ancient pragmatism and I might also say
it was the birth of ancient humanism
and there was also a disillusionment
about religion
the gods had let the people down
and so now we have a kind of
pre-socratic
period of secularism now I use those
particular descriptive terms for a
reason because when we step away from
the Greek age and look at our own
culture today many of the critics
describe our own culture at the end of
the 20th century as humanistic
as secular and as pragmatic and so it's
important for us if we can look at an
ancient culture that mirrors so many of
the life situations that we encounter in
our own civilization today maybe we can
learn something from it but into this
vacuum of the decline of Greek
civilization stepped a group of teachers
who became very important and they were
called the sophists
the safest which is a word that comes
from the Greek word Sophia which is the
word wisdom in fact the very word
philosophy means Sofia the love of
wisdom
now the sophists consider themselves as
the word suggests sages they were
learned people and at the beginning of
the movement of this office there was a
certain
respectability and dignity to their
endeavors
but with the decline of the civilization
came also the corruption of the sophist
movement and I have to say just as a
little parenthesis as an aside
we don't have a lot of first-hand
information about the sophists
themselves I mean we're not totally in
the dark about it but so much of the
information that we have about this
office and Antiquity come to us through
those dialogues of Plato that have
survived to this day and Plato in his
day had an extremely negative view of
this office so when we consider ancient
sophism we're looking at them Through
The Eyes of one who was sharply critical
of them and so we have to keep that in
mind as we analyze them but in any case
we have words in our language that have
their origin in this movement the word
sophomore
the word sophistry which is a negative
term
and the word sophisticated
which may have a positive connotation
when we say that somebody has a
sophisticated knowledge of something we
mean that they have more than a passing
superficial grasp of things but that
they've gone into it rather deeply but
really
in the development of language
originally the term even the term
sophisticated had a negative connotation
meaning somebody who was simply
superficial who gave an outward display
of beauty or an outward display of
knowledge or
ability but once you scratch the surface
you don't find much substance there well
these words that come down into our
language have been heavily influenced by
the negative view of this movement now
the surface as I say were professional
teachers what I mean by professional
teachers is that they charged fees for
their pedagogy they were itinerant
teachers that is they went from Village
to Village and from town to town to give
their courses and their teaching
but what had happened in the political
structure of Athens
is that the movement was in the
direction of more and more of a
democratic process where the leaders
were not Kings who passed their power on
to their progeny or noblemen but the
leaders more and more were were emerging
as a result of popular elections
and also there were significant changes
in the judicial system of Athens where
we have the development of the jury
system
and the juries would vote on the verdict
of the accused
and so now we have a culture
where the art of public speaking
now is at a premium
because those who are most articulate
and most persuasive
who can move the passions And the
emotions of the people
have the best chance of becoming the
elected officials and hence the
governors of the populace and also the
attorneys
who can move the passions of those
impaneled as jury members have the
ability to persuade the jury to come to
the verdict that they desire
now all of those things are part and
parcel of the society in which we find
ourselves today
but now the sofas in their teaching as I
said we're concerned with practical
matters they were pragmatists the truth
is defined not by some metaphysical
ultimate correspondence to reality but
the truth is discerned by what works
what works in Practical terms in the
marketplace where we live they were the
original Madison Avenue admin
whose tests for their effectiveness in
advertising was not whether the claims
for the product actually were true but
rather how effective they were in
getting people to purchase the product
so truth was not their interest
persuasion was their interest and the
school that they developed most the
significantly was that of rhetoric
well we still have rhetoric in in our
own culture today and we identify it
with the art of public speaking
but for this office again
the artfulness of rhetoric
focused on the ability of the speaker to
move the emotions of the here so that
they would be persuaded in a certain
direction
now we still care about persuasion
I tell my students in the Seminary when
they come into my courses I say you're
studying theology here and I think you
need to be for warned when you step into
my classroom that I'm not interested
simply in transferring historical
information from my notebook to yours
I'm out to get your mind
I want to persuade you of the truth of
these principles I'm engaged in
apologetics I'm trying not only to
explain these principles but I'm trying
to defend them and to capture your
minds in the sense of proving to you
that these are sound principles and
principles that you ought to embrace and
live by now we're still trying to
persuade but in that case the goal
ultimately is to persuade people to
acquiesce to truth
not just to persuade them
for vested interest for personal
interests for economic or political aims
but what had what had happened with this
office is their whole focus on
persuasion was for mean pragmatic ends
we think of the Moss the knees the
famous orator who practices his speeches
by filling his mouth with pebbles so
that he could train his lips and his
tongue to be super articulate
in the task now it's also at this time
that we find the Advent of a very
important
pre-socratic philosopher whose name was
protagoras and protagoras is often
consider to be the father of humanism
because he gave us the Latin phrase homo
mensura homo Mansura man the measure and
what he was saying is that man is the
measure of all things now again calling
attention to focusing our attention not
on some Never Never Land a philosophical
speculation of metaphysics but to
concentrate our interests in the welfare
of human beings in the Here and Now
another important philosopher at this
time was a man whose name was gorgeous
well that was his whole name it wasn't
Gorgeous George and it wasn't gorgeous
in the sense of pretty his name was
gorgeous and he was important because he
was one of the early Skeptics
and he said
that uh
that the good that which is good or that
which is right
is that that men perceive to be that
which works for their own vested
interests let me say it again the right
or the good is defined in terms of what
advances your own agenda your own vested
interest now think of this in terms of
modern
self-interest groups Lobby groups and
all the rest where we just say well
everybody has a right to advance their
own concerns and we have reduced the
very concept of the good or the right
to human preferences
in an age of relativism that says there
are no absolute Goods or there's no
absolute right or wrong it's however you
perceive it whatever you prefer it to be
that is has roots way deep in Western
history with the skeptical philosophy of
people like gorgeous now it's into that
venue into that environment that
Socrates stepped
he was passionately concerned
that what was going on around him
would be fatal to science
to The Pursuit Of Truth in any Arena
to the Dignity of the court system
and of the political structures
themselves
and at the very heart of his concern was
what he perceived to be the wholesale
loss of virtue
they can Bennett's book on virtue that
was recently a bestseller in our own
culture where we are facing the same
kind of disintegration in our culture
today a fundamental loss
of virtue
and Socrates was not satisfied to accept
this as the Fate
of Athens and so he went about the city
engaging students engaging people in
deep conversations trying to awaken them
to the deeper questions of truth and the
great issues that faced the nation of
his day
he wasn't con he wasn't content simply
to examine his own life
but he wanted to get other people to
begin challenging the assumptions of
their culture and to begin examining
their own premises and their own
thinking
and so he's famous
for several things not the least of
which is that he is the one of course
who invented what we call
the Socratic method
and the Socratic method of discovering
truth
is the method of dialogue
he would engage people in dialogue and
ask them probing questions
and as the person would respond Socrates
would help them move along in their own
self-examination by asking more
questions and deeper questions in other
words he didn't just stand in the middle
of the Town Square and preach and
deliver lectures he was more like
Lieutenant Colombo you know he'd say do
you mind if I ask you a personal
question and he would then engage people
in dialogue and you see
the the value of that method of teaching
when you see the vast Corpus of writings
that his most famous pupil wrote Plato
when we think of Plato and his writings
what do we call them the dialogues of
Plato where there's an issue that is
introduced at the beginning of the
dialogue and then he moderates a
discussion that goes on between
representatives of different schools of
thought and then finally Socrates comes
in the dialogue and unravels the Mystery
of whatever issue it is that they are
discussing
and so Socrates thought that by
forcing people to think
he could move them from that superficial
plane of sophism and get them into a
more deep consideration
of Truth he was what we might say the
original Paradigm of Education
his goal was to educate and that word
educate means literally to lead out of
ilduche the leader remember and and Ed
or the e at the beginning means from or
out of e duche educate
to lead out of to lead out of what
to lead out of ignorance
well Socrates said the very first thing
that has to happen for any true
knowledge to be gained for anyone to
ever become knowledgeable to gain an
understanding of virtue and to truly be
educated was the admission of ignorance
and that's one of the hardest things for
any of us to admit that we are ignorant
about anything
but Socrates said once the person admits
that he or she is ignorant now the
possibility is open to lead them
to a deeper understanding of Truth now
again his principle was concerned his
principal concern
was to come to an understanding of
virtue
virtue being the good or the right
and he believed this not only in an
abstract way but in a very concrete way
he believed that how we Act
how we behave
is in the first analysis a matter of
proper knowledge he didn't Embrace a
Biblical concept of original sin as we
would but what he was saying is that
part of the problem we have with our
behavior is that we don't know
what right behavior is
before we can possibly act in a good way
we have to first understand
what a good form of behavior is and so
he Focus his attention on helping people
understand
virtue
what is honesty
what is industry what is Justice and he
would push them beyond the idea of of
vested interests or self-interest to
come to the deeper understanding of
these concepts by which human life human
virtue and the virtue of a society
stand or false now
one can look at Socrates and say his
life with Socrates and say that his life
was a failure
he was executed
he was charged with being an atheist
because he rejected the uh the Pagan
deities of the city but more seriously
with corrupting the Youth of Athens
because he was challenging their ideas
and he was forced to drink the hemlock
and Plato was his most famous student
and Plato presumably attended the
execution of Socrates and met with
Socrates in his cell and discussed his
impending death with him and was
overwhelmed by the remarkable calmness
and confidence that Socrates had with
respect to life after death
well as I said Socrates is to our
knowledge didn't write anything
virtually what we know of his thinking
and we know of his ideas comes through
the speeches put in his mouth by his
most famous plate student Plato whom we
will examine in our next session